Palliative care is the care of patients who have an advanced, progressive illness that is not curable, and in general, will probably result in death within weeks or months (as opposed to many years). As such there is an emphasis on quality of life and symptom control. At times there will also be a focus on active interventions to reverse acute complications of illness and, in doing so, prolong a person’s life. At other times there will be a focus on maintaining comfort and so avoiding interventions and instead allowing a natural death. Palliative care extends past the physical to embrace emotional, spiritual and psychosocial aspects of the care of patients and their families. This is what makes it an art as well as a science. The emphasis of this book is about succinct principles and medication guidelines only, with the assumption that other aspects of the biopsychosocial determinants of health are also being explored and managed.

“You matter because you are you, and you matter to the end of your life. We will do all we can not only to help you die peacefully, but also to live until you die.” – Dame Cicely Saunders

“There is a time for everything, and a season for every activity under the heavens: a time to be born and a time to die, a time to plant and a time to uproot, a time to kill and a time to heal, a time to tear down and a time to build, a time to weep and a time to laugh, a time to mourn and a time to dance, a time to scatter stones and a time to gather them, a time to embrace and a time to refrain from embracing, a time to search and a time to give up…”   - Ecclesiastes 1

Appendix - Supportive and Palliative Care Tool (SPICT)

The University of Edinburgh’s SPICT is used to help identify people whose health is deteriorating. Assess them for unmet supportive and palliative care needs. Plan care. Look for any general indicators of poor or deteriorating health, as well as for the specific clinical indicators noted below:

Unplanned hospital admission(s)

Performance status is poor or deteriorating, with limited reversibility (e.g. the person stays in bed or in a chair for more than half the day)

Depends on others for care due to increasing physical and/or mental health problems. The person’s carer needs more help and support

The person has had  significant  weight loss  over the last few months, or remains underweight

Persistent symptoms despite optimal treatment of underlying condition(s)

The person (or family) asks for palliative care; chooses to reduce, stop or not have treatment; or wishes to focus on quality of life

Cancer

Functional ability deteriorating due to progressive cancer.

Too frail for cancer treatment or treatment is for symptom control.

Functional ability deteriorating due to progressive cancer.

Too frail for cancer treatment or treatment is for symptom control.

Dementia/ frailty

Unable to dress, walk or eat without help.

Eating and drinking less; difficulty with swallowing.

Urinary and faecal incontinence. Not able to communicate by speaking; little social interaction.

Frequent falls; fractured femur.

Recurrent febrile episodes or infections; aspiration pneumonia.

Neurological disease

Progressive deterioration in physical and/or cognitive function despite optimal therapy.

Speech problems with increasing difficulty communicating and/or progressive difficulty with swallowing.

Recurrent aspiration  pneumonia; breathless or respiratory failure.

Persistent paralysis after stroke with significant  loss of function and ongoing disability.

Heart/ vascular disease

Heart failure or extensive, untreatable coronary artery disease; with breathlessness or chest pain at rest or on minimal effort.

Severe, inoperable peripheral vascular disease.

Respiratory disease

Severe, chronic lung disease; with breathlessness at rest or on minimal effort between exacerbations.

Persistent hypoxia needing long term oxygen therapy.

Has needed ventilation for respiratory failure or ventilation is contraindicated.

Kidney disease

Stage 4 or 5 chronic kidney disease (eGFR < 30ml/min) with deteriorating health.

Kidney failure complicating other life limiting conditions or treatments.

Stopping or not starting dialysis.

Liver disease

Cirrhosis with one or more complications in the past year: diuretic resistant ascites, hepatic encephalopathy, hepatorenal syndrome, bacterial peritonitis, recurrent variceal bleeds

Liver transplant is not possible.

In patients in the categories above review the current care and care planning including:

Review medications
Consider specialist assessment
Agree current and future plan with person and family
Support carers
Record and communicate the care plan.

This book is intended for use by primary and secondary care doctors (especially in Queensland) caring for patients with terminal illnesses.

It is not meant to be a replacement for other textbooks – how could a book this small ever do that! Nor is it intended as a set of strict protocols that should always be followed. Rather, this book is intended for health professionals who have a good background knowledge of general medicine and pharmacology and can use that background knowledge and their experience in conjunction with the advice found on these pages.

The treatments suggested in this book will not be appropriate in all circumstances. This book supplements, but should not replace, other sources (e.g. the AMH; education and training; seeking advice from the palliative care team). Medication adverse effects, contra-indications and drug-drug interactions are not discussed in any significant detail in this book. This means that the usual competencies of clinicians and prescribers are assumed. If in doubt, seek advice from other sources.

Focal seizures with secondary generalization are a complication of brain tumours, both primary and secondary. In most cases (except possibly in patients with melanoma with multiple cerebral deposits with haemorrhage), primary prophylaxis with anti-epileptics does not reduce the risk. However, preventative anti-epileptic medications are usually appropriate after a first seizure.

Seizures may also occur because of metabolic disturbances (e.g. hyponatraemia) or as part of a pre-existing epilepsy. As with all problems in palliative care, the management needs to be tailored to the individual patient based on the stage of illness and patient’s function and previously expressed wishes.

Treating a seizure – the acute setting

A quick-acting benzodiazepines is usually the best initial treatment.

If outside of hospital ->

Clonazepam 1mg subcut (or IM) or clonazepam drops 1mg (10 drops) sublingually
Exclude hypoglycaemia
Repeat the dose of clonazepam 15 minutes later if the seizure is ongoing
If the cause is unknown or if the family is not prepared to manage seizures, hospital admission is appropriate. It may be appropriate to call an ambulance, especially if the seizure is still happening. If the cause is known and the seizure has stopped, hospital admission may not be required.

If in a hospital setting ->

Get help and discuss with an experienced doctor
Midazolam 5mg slowly IV until seizure stops (or midazolam 5mg subcut or IM)
Watch SaO2 and support the airway
Exclude hypoglycaemia
If seizure has not settled within 15 minutes  ->

Repeat the benzodiazepine dose

If the seizure continues, further benzodiazepines are unlikely to be effective. Seek urgent advice from a senior doctor regarding the appropriateness of referral to the intensive care unit

If intensive care is appropriate, call intensive care and consider giving IV phenytoin

If the patient is thought to be imminently dying, prepare the family that death may be near. Phenobarbitone can be used for seizures refractory to midazolam.

Preventing further seizures

Treat any underlying precipitants. If already on anti-epileptics, modify dose if appropriate.

For seizures due to cerebral tumours, sodium valproate or levetiracetam are good options:

Sodium valproate 200mg twice daily (typical maximum 800mg twice daily)
OR
Levetiracetam (streamlined authority) 500mg orally twice daily (maximum dose: 1,500 mg twice daily)

Remember to advise a patient against driving following a seizure.

For seizures in a patient entering the last days of life, replace oral anti-epileptics with:

Clonazepam 1mg subcut PRN for any further seizures
AND
Clonazepam 2mg over 24 hours via CSCI
OR
Levetiracetam via CSCI over 24 hours (e.g. 1,000mg)

Appendix - Methadone

Methadone in palliative patients should only be used under the direction of a palliative care specialist. Speak to one before initiating methadone.

Methadone often provides good analgesia in patients with terminal illnesses. It has unusual pharmacokinetics with a very long half-life of days and toxicity can occur unexpectedly after a week or more of an apparently well tolerated dose regimen.

Indication: Pain refractory to other treatment, especially pain associated with a neuropathic component, opioid-tolerance or central sensitisation

Some advantages of methadone

Dosing unaffected by renal failure.

Often brings significant benefits at low doses allowing for major reduction in the dose other opioids. It may also be beneficial in opioid-induced hyperalgesia.

Commencing methadone

Guidelines for using methadone in the palliative context vary widely. This guideline suggests a conservative approach where low-dose methadone is added on top the patient’s current analgesia.

Before starting exclude a prolonged QTc by performing an ECG.

Start at 5mg orally at night. Continue any pre-existing regular and PRN analgesia.

Increasing the dose

If inadequate analgesia is achieved within 3-5 days, the dose can be increased to 5mg twice daily. Monitor for adverse effects.

The dose can be increased further in small 5mg increments ever 5-7 days if necessary however speak to a senior palliative care doctor.

Recheck the ECG after 2-4 weeks to ensure that the QTc interval remains < 0.5.

Consider gradually reducing the dose of other background opioids such as a fentanyl patch whilst titrating up the methadone, especially if adverse effects or a poor response to these opioids (or opioid-induced hyperalgesia) is suspected.

Long-term dosing and stopping methadone

If significant side effects occur (e.g. sedation and reduced respiratory rate) then stop the methadone and reduce other opioids. In serious cases naloxone may be needed.

If there is no apparent improvement with methadone cease it.

If there is good analgesia, consider reducing the dose of other long-acting opioids and continuing the methadone longer term.

Precautions

Previous arrhythmias

Prolonged QTc > 0.5

Any reason to be cautious with any opioid

Adverse Effects

Sedation

Respiratory depression

Arrhythmias associated with QT prolongation

Constipation

Nausea

Subcut Methadone

10mg oral ≈ 10mg subcut

Give as twice daily subcut boluses or a CSCI

Compatible with:

Cyclizine (use water for injection)

Haloperidol

Ketamine

Levomepromazine

Midazolam

Haloperidol + midazolam

Ketamine + midazolam

Levomepromazine + hyoscine butylbromide

Levomepromazine + midazolam

Levomepromazine + hyoscine butylbromide + midazolam

See also: Fentanly syringe driver compatibilities

Fentanyl patch prescribing tips

Fentanyl patches hold the drug in a matrix.

The amount of drug delivered is related to the surface area of the patch, so a 50mcg/hour patch is twice the surface area of a 25mcg/hour patch.

The patch needs to be in contact with the skin completely, for the correct amount of fentanyl to be absorbed.

If the edges are lifting up, the patient will be receiving sub optimal fentanyl.

Fentanyl patches work by releasing fentanyl into the subcutaneous fat which is then absorbed into the systemic circulation.

If the patient is significantly cachexic, the drug will not be absorbed. This is important to understand. For example, when swapping from a 100mcg/hour patch to oral morphine you would generally consider prescribing somewhere around 300mg of oral morphine in 24hours, however in a cachectic patient where the drug wasn’t being absorbed well, the patient may only need a much smaller oral morphine equivalent of say, for example 60mg over 24 hours.

PRN or “as required” breakthrough fentanyl comes in injection (non-PBS), lozenge,  sublingual and buccal formulations

These PRN doses do not bear a direct relationship to patch size. For example, a breakthrough of sublingual 100mcg fentanyl does NOT equate to 100mcg/h patch.

When the patch is applied the first time, analgesia will emerge in the first 24 hours, but can take many days to start to approach steady state.

Therefore do not titrate up the patch dose rapidly over a few day because doing so will significantly risk causing opioid overdose.

Never commence an opioid naïve patient on a fentanyl patch; there is significant risk of opioid overdose.
Applying heat on a patch will increase its rate of absorption, causing opioid toxicity.

For some patients, the patches only last 48 hours instead of 72 hours. In this patients, change the patch every 48 hours, rather than increasing the dose.

Sublingual and buccal fentanyl prescription tips

There are various formulations of buccal and sublingual fentanyl available that are marketed as rapid acting opioids.

Do not use in opioid naïve patients.

Rapid acting fentanyl preparations should only be used if a patient is already on a regular long-acting opioid (equivalent to at least 60mg of daily oral morphine).

The effective dose of rapid acting fentanyl preparations cannot be estimated by considering the background oral opioid as can usually be done for other immediate release opioids.

Therefore when starting rapidly acting fentanyl preparations, the usual advice is to start at the lowest possible dose (e.g. 100 micrograms) and titrate upwards as necessary, regardless of the background long-acting opioid dose.

Mouth ulcers and mucositis can affect the absorption of sublingual and buccal fentanyl.

Rapid acting fentanyl preparations typically have a more rapid onset of action than oral hydromorphone, morphine and oxycodone and therefore are worth considering for patients with predictable incident pain.

For example, consider prescribing 15-minutes prior to dressing for a patient who has severe arm pain from a humerus metastasis each day when getting dressed.

Predicting life expectancy is not easy and it is as much an art as a science. Of course none of us know the future and so it is not helpful to be too definite about a patient’s prognosis.

None-the-less, being able to make a reasonable, educated guess about a patient’s illness trajectory and the likely prognosis is important because:

Some patients (and their relatives) want to know this (although it is equally true that some do not)
It helps inform decisions regarding how aggressively to treat complications as they arise

If discussing prognosis and life expectancy with a patient, be sensitive, compassionate and honest in your approach. Do not be afraid to be unsure and to defer to other doctors and specialists who have more experience in treating the patient’s particular illness.

A key element to determining prognosis is to understand the natural history of the particular disease that the patient suffers from. It is helpful to remember that new treatments are changing the trajectory and course of many illnesses.

Traditionally advanced cancer has been relatively straight-forward in terms of prognostication, although with the advent of immunotherapy this is changing. The course and natural history of end-stage organ failure (e.g. liver failure due to cirrhosis) is very variable and it is harder to be reasonably sure about the prognosis when compared to advanced metastatic cancer. Acute deteriorations are more often reversible and so knowing when to withdraw (or not offer) treatment can be quite difficult.

The following information boxes, tools and rules of thumb may be helpful in determining prognosis. None of them is perfect, however, so use them in conjunction with common sense.

Additional tools found in the appendix that help prognosticate include the SPICT and PCOC scores.

Advanced cancer
Cirrhosis
Chronic kidney disease
Congestive cardiac failure
Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease

Consider the aetiologies of dyspnoea and treat these as appropriate, taking the patient’s overall state and prognosis into consideration. Thinking about the diagnosis is important when there is dyspnoea that worsens without good explanation. In particular, consider ->

Pulmonary emboli (think of this especially if dyspnoea out of proportion to extent of disease)
Pleural effusion (or a pericardial effusion or massive ascites)
Acute respiratory infection
Superior vena cava obstruction (look for oedema and distended veins in the head and upper limbs)

Treating the above conditions can bring significant symptomatic relief and prolong a person’s life.

Condition specific symptomatic treatments to also consider:
Options for pulmonary oedema

Increase diuretic therapy. Frusemide can be given via CSCI. Higher doses are needed in severe renal failure
Control rapid atrial fibrillation (e.g. with digoxin)
Long-acting nitrates, especially at night (e.g. isosorbide dinitrate) if blood pressure permits

Options for exacerbation of COPD

Short burst of increased dose of steroids, e.g. prednisolone 37.5mg daily for a a few days
Antibiotics
Optimise bronchodilator therapy (e.g. review inhaler technique; salbutamol more frequently)

Options for motor neuron disease

Non-invasive ventilation (NIV). Assessment usually accessed by referral to a respiratory team. Deciding to have or not have NIV is a huge decision and involves delicate discussions. NIV may be appropriate if any of these present:

Abnormal nocturnal oximetry OR
FVC < 50% predicted OR
Orthopnoea

Options for anaemia

Transfusion (e.g. if Hb < 85)

Options for multiple pulmonary metastases or lymphangitis carcinomatosis

Dexamethasone 8 mg daily

A written breathlessness management plan can help patients deal with acute episodes of worsened dyspnoea.

Finally consider symptomatic treatments regardless of cause ->

Movement of air (e.g. via a fan) usually helps.

Consider OT/physio and psychology input.

If there is dyspnoea at rest -> use of opioids is controversial, although traditionally low doses of opioids were considered potentially helpful, e.g. for opioid-naïve patients

Morphine SR 5 mg orally twice daily or 10mg once daily
PLUS
Immediate release morphine 2.5 mg orally 2-hourly PRN
(See opioid section for information on dosing and opioid choice)

If there is significant anxiety and fear associated with dyspnoea -> anxiolytics may help; choice partially depends on life expectancy (non-PBS indication for both)

Months -> Citalopram 10mg orally daily
Weeks -> Clonazepam drops 3 drops sublingually or orally 4-hourly PRN

If there is evidence of hypoxia -> oxygen may help

Oxygen continuously for dyspnoea at rest (titrate to symptoms)
OR
Oxygen 2-4 litres on exertion and PRN for exertional dyspnoea
(Use oxygen cautiously in patients who are at risk of CO2 retention, e.g. those with COPD)

Prescribing medications frequently used in palliative care (especially ones at the end of life) within the hospital setting is usually relatively straight-forward however in the community it can be more problematic because certain drugs are not covered by the PBS (i.e. private prescriptions are required). Some helpful tips for prescribing in the community that are accurate for 2021 are listed below. These tips primarily, although not exclusively, relate to medications for end-of-life care in the home setting.

For injectable opioids:

Injectable oxycodone and fentanyl are not available through the PBS whereas injectable morphine and hydromorphone are.

For benzodiazepines:

Injectable midazolam is not available through the PBS. Prescription of injectable clonazepam for palliative care patients became available through the PBS in 2021.

For anti-secretory agents:

Injectable glycopyrrolate and hyoscine hydrobromide are not available through the PBS whereas injectable hyoscine butylbromide (Buscopan) through a streamlined authority number is.

For co-analgesics:

Gabapentin is an authority-required drug whereas pregabalin is a stream-lined authority drug.
Methadone is a restricted-benefit medication (“severe disabling pain unresponsive to non-opioid analgesics”)
Amitriptyline and valproate are available without PBS restrictions.

Mixing medications in subcutaneous infusions can cause problems if there are drug incompatibilities that cause reactions. Always use caution when mixing medications looking especially for crystallization. The following tables lists some compatible combinations – these are not an exhaustive list. If unsure about a combination, speak to a palliative care pharmacist, physician or nurse specialist.

Sodium chloride 0.9% is the diluent used routinely in Australia and is used as the diluent throughout these guidelines unless otherwise stated.

Some important considerations:

Cyclizine is diluted with Water for Injection. There is a risk of precipitation when cyclizing is mixed with drugs formulated in a solution containing chloride ions or if pH > 6.8.  Cyclizine is incompatible with hyoscine butylbromide and fentanyl.
Glycopyrrolate is acidic (pH 2.3-4.3) and should not be added to mixtures where pH > 6
Haloperidol > 1mg/mL in sodium chloride 0.9% may precipitate
Ranitidine has shown to be incompatible with midazolam and levomepromazine (may be concentration dependent)

Morphine compatabilities

Oxycodone compatabilities

Hydromorphone compatabilities

Fentanyl compatabilities

Opioid-free compatabilities

The following drugs cannot be combined in the same syringe with other drugs

Diclofenac

|

Frusemide

|

Levetiracetam

Phenobarbitone

|

Lignocaine

|

Valproate

References:

1 - Dickman and Schneider. The Syringe Driver 3rd Edition. 2015

2 - www.palliativedrugs.com

3 - Eastern Metropolitan Region Palliative Care (Victoria). Syringe Driver Drugs. 2016

4 - Isle of Wight Syringe Driver Compatibility Guidelines. 2016

Appendix - Lidocaine

Lidocaine (previously lignocaine) in palliative patients should only be used under the direction of a palliative care specialist. Speak to one before initiating lidocaine.

A subcutaneous infusion of lidocaine (non-PBS) is a useful treatment option in patients with a terminal illness who have severe pain refractory to other treatments. It requires careful assessment, consent and monitoring by a clinician familiar with its place, use and evidence-base relative to alternatives.

Indication: Pain (especially neuropathic pain) refractory to other analgesia.

Before starting

Exclude contraindications by performing an ECG. Do not use in patients with a history of an arrhythmia without first discussing with a cardiologist. Exhaust all other available treatment options before using in patients in the “precautions” group.

Check the blood pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate and sedation and pain scores.

Communicate and gain consent.

Commencing an infusion

Start at a dose of 500mg via continuous subcutaneous infusion over 24 hours. In a thin and elderly person, consider beginning at 250 mg over 24 hours.

Monitor HR, RR, BP and sedation score at 2, 4 and 8 hours and thereafter three times daily. Perform an ECG the day following infusion.

Increasing the dose

If inadequate analgesia is achieved, consider increasing the infusion rate by 250-500mg every 24-48 hours to a maximum dose of 1,500mg per day. With each increase in dose, recheck the ECG within 24 hours.

Stopping an infusion

If bradycardia, hypotension, a cardiac arrhythmia or any other significant adverse effects occur, cease the infusion.

If, 24-hours after reaching the maximum dose, there has been no improvement in pain, cease the infusion.

If good analgesia occurs, consider gradually tapering the infusion by reducing in 250-500 mg increments every 24-48 hours. Consider complementing the reduction in lignocaine with a corresponding increase in other analgesic agents, e.g. methadone.

Absolute Contraindications

AV block

Stokes-Adams attacks

Wolf-Parkinson-White syndrome

Previous sensitivity

Precautions

Arrhythmias

Cardiac failure

Seizures

Liver failure

Renal failure

Adverse Effects

Most are dose-related and are unlikely with doses under 2mg/kg/hour.

Cardiovascular – hypotension, bradycardia

Neuromuscular – light-headedness, tingling, muscle spasm, dysphasia, seizures, drowsiness

Respiratory arrest

Appendix - Ascitic tap

Indication: To relieve abdominal discomfort (and dyspnoea) due to significant amounts of ascites.

Equipment Required
Sterile gloves
Iodine scrub (to wash hands)
Basic dressing pack
Anti-septic solution (e.g. chlorhexidine)
Small gauge needle (e.g. 23 gauge)
Small syringe (e.g. 5 or 10 ml)
Local anaesthetic (e.g. 1% lidocaine)
Large gauge long IV line or equivalent (e.g. 14 guage AngioCath or Yueh Centesis Catheter)
Drainge bag (e.g. 2 litre drainage bag with male connection)
Sticky-tape (e.g. Leukopor)
Dressing (e.g. Tegarderm)
Sharps container
PLUS
Hand-held or portable ultrasound

Technique

Exclude contra-indications. Gain consent
Lie the patient supine with the abdomen exposed
Select a site where there is shifting dullness. Confirm the presence of a deep pocket of ascites here with an ultrasound and note its depth. Mark the skin clearly with a pen
Wash your hands and put on sterile gloves
Clean the skin with anti-septic solution
Draw up lidocaine. Using a small-gauge needle, insert the needle at a right-angle to the skin, drawing back as you proceed until you get a flash-back of ascites. If you have difficult or do not get a flash-back then abandon the procedure (and organize via radiology), otherwise slowly inject the anaesthetic whilst withdrawing the needle. Wait a few minutes.
Insert the drainage catheter at a right-angle to the skin. On getting flash-back or feeling the “give” of insertion through the peritoneum, insert the needle another centimetre and then withdraw it whilst inserting the plastic tube fully.
Ascitic fluid should now be draining. Attach a drainage bag. Ensure the catheter and bag tubing is attached firmly to the abdominal wall (e.g. with sticky-tape).
Allow drainage to occur. You may need to empty the bag a number of times. Drainage may take several hours. For ascites due to portal hypertension, albumin replacement is recommended if draining more than 5 litres

Albumin Replacement Formula:

Give 100ml of 20% albumin for every 2.5 litres drained

Once the drainage stops or slows significantly, remove the catheter and cover the wound site with a dressing. If leakage of ascites occurs in the hours and days following the procedure, a colostomy bag can be used to prevent soaking of shirt and sheets.
Monitor blood pressure and pulse hourly for 4-hours post procedure and review the patient if these become abnormal.

Potential complications include:
Infection (e.g. cellulitis)
Bleeding
Bowel perforation or organ damage
Hypotension
Leakage of ascites

The first 4 complications are rare and risk can be minimized by:

Using a sterile technique
Checking for bleeding risks and INR and  platelets prior to procedure
Using an ultrasound to confirm a deep pocket of ascites
Albumin replacement (for large taps of ascites due to portal hypertension)

Be catious if:
INR > 1.5 | Platelets < 100
Consider correction if:
INR > 2 | Platelets < 50

Appendix - Ketamine

Ketamine in palliative patients should only be used under the direction of a palliative care specialist. Speak to one before initiating ketamine.

Ketamine (non-PBS) is an option in patients with a terminal illness who have severe pain refractory to other treatments although the evidence is mixed and conflicting.

Indication: Pain (especially neuropathic pain) refractory to other analgesia.

Before starting

Check blood pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate and conscious level. Exclude contraindications. If longer term use (>weeks) is anticipated, ensure hepatotoxicity and urotoxicity are considered when obtaining consent and arranging monitoring.

Prescribe PRN haloperidol and PRN midazolam for hallucinations and anxiety respectively.

Continue to check blood pressure, heart and respiratory rate and conscious level three times daily.

Subcutaneous administration regimen

Commence 100mg via continuous SC infusion over 24 hours. In a thin and elderly person, consider beginning at 50mg over 24 hours.

PRN ketamine 25mg 4-hourly can be prescribed in addition to PRN opioids.

If inadequate analgesia is achieved, consider increasing the infusion rate by 100mg every 24-48 hours to a maximum dose of 500mg per day. Continue to monitor blood pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate and conscious level.

Oral administration regimen

Ketamine can also be taken orally but dosing protocols vary widely.

Commence 10mg orally three times daily and 10mg PRN 4 hourly. If inadequate analgesia is achieved, consider increasing in 10mg increments every 24-48 hours to a maximum dose of 100mg three times daily. Continue to monitor blood pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate and conscious level

Stopping ketamine

If significant side effects occur (especially sedation and reduced respiratory rate) then stop the ketamine.  If, 24 hours after reaching the maximum dose, there has been no improvement in pain, stop the ketamine (tapering is not required).

If good analgesia occurs, consider gradually tapering the dose by similar increments and rate as the above titration. If pain recurs, consider either an oral or subcut maintenance dose (discuss monitoring arrangements for hepatotoxicity and urotoxicity with a consultant) or another analgesic agent, e.g. methadone.

Absolute Contraindications

Previous serious reaction

Recent or poorly controlled seizures

Raised intracranial pressure

Uncontrolled hypertension

Precautions

Brain metastases

Possible raised ICP

Previous strokes

Severe cardiac failure

Tachyarrhythmias

History of glaucoma

Adverse Effects

Improved efficacy of other opioids resulting in opioid toxicity

Sympathomimetic effects - raised blood pressure, tachycardia

Psychomimetic effects – vivid dreams, hallucinations, agitation, sedation

Urotoxicity – suspect if recurrent UTI-like symptoms

Subcut Ketamine

5mg oral ≈ 5mg SC

Compatible with: (use NaCl 0.9% unless otherwise stated):

Fentanyl

Haloperidol

Hydromorphone

Levomepromazine

Methadone

Midazolam

Morphine

Haloperidol + midazolam

Morphine + haloperidol

Morphine + midazolam

It is wise to consult early with a palliative care consultant as bowel obstruction in malignancy is a dynamic and complex situation. The underlying pathology may cause a physical obstruction (“mechanical bowel obstruction”) or there may be pathology causing a predominantly ileus type scenario where the bowel stops working properly (“functional bowel obstruction”). There is often a combination of both.

“Functional bowel obstruction”

Suspect this in patients with peritoneal disease with vomiting, markedly reduced frequency of bowel movement and an absence of colicky abdominal pain. Up to 50% of women with ovarian cancer will experience a degree of “functional obstruction” because the abdominal and pelvic cavity becomes matted and stuck down with autonomic dysfunction due to tumour infiltration. Bowel sounds may be quiet.

First-line treatment includes:

Consider NG tube and IV or subcut fluids if there is significant vomiting
Metoclopramide 30mg CSCI over 24 hours to promote peristalsis. Titrate up to 60mg daily if necessary. If colicky pains occurs, stop metoclopramide as this worsens colic and manage as a mechanical bowel obstruction.
Stool softeners such as sodium docusate 200mg twice daily orally or macrogol as tolerated
Dexamethasone 8mg subcut daily (orally it won’t be absorbed)

“Mechanical Bowel Obstruction”

A mechanical bowel obstruction may develop de novo (e.g. due to mass effect in colorectal cancer or pancreas cancer) or a “functional bowel obstruction” may develop into a more typical mechanical obstruction. Patients present with colicky abdominal pain, worsening vomiting abdominal distension, and absolute constipation. Investigating with a CT scan and considering stenting or surgery is often appropriate.

Treat vomiting and distension with anti-secretory agents:

Consider NG tube insertion + IV or subcut fluids
Hyoscine butylbromide (PBS authority) 80mg via CSCI over 24 hours
And
Ranitidine (non-PBS) 150mg via CSCI over 24 hours

Additional symptomatic relief is important, including:

Haloperidol for any ongoing nausea (e.g. 0.5mg 2-hourly PRN)
An opioid for analgesia

If the aim is to try and restore bowel movements, consider:

Dexamethasone 8mg SC daily (reduce peri-tumour oedema)
Sodium docusate orally and softeners per rectum in case constipation / hard stools are playing a role

If vomiting persists:

If minimal oral intake, add octreotide (special access scheme) 500mcg via CSCI over 24 hours (an anti-secretory agent)
Anti-secretory drugs will be less effective if eating and drinking – consider an NG tube or venting PEG

If nausea persists, switch haloperidol to levomepromazine (special access scheme) 12.5mg via CSCI over 24 hours.

To also consider:

Imaging with a CT scan can (a) confirm the diagnosis and (b) determine if obstruction is unifocal or multifocal

If unifocal obstruction on CT scan, consider asking for advice regarding whether the lesion is amenable  to endoscopic stenting or surgical intervention

In intractable nausea and vomiting, consider a venting gastrostomy (speak to a gastroenterologist or interventional radiologist)

Anticipate constipation, especially in patients prescribed opioids, and start prophylactic laxatives where appropriate. If appropriate encourage increased fluids and fruit intake and encourage mobilization if appropriate. Avoid ispaghula (e.g. Fybogel) as it worsens constipation if fluid intake is inadequate.

Initial therapy -> oral therapy with a softener and/or stimulant is appropriate

Docusate 1 tablet twice daily regularly (or PRN) (a softener for hard stools)
AND/OR
Sennoside 1 tablet twice daily (or PRN) or picosulfate oral 10 drops twice daily (a stimulant)

Doses can be titrated up or down based on level of constipation. Titrate up the softener if stool hard and/or colicky discomfort present; titrate stimulants up if patient struggling to expel soft stool.

If constipation continues -> consider rectal treatments, e.g.

Bisacodyl 1 suppository daily PRN (if stools soft)
Microlax 1 enema daily PRN (if stool hard)

For severe, refractory constipation -> options include

High dose softener (PicoPrep)
High bowel intervention, e.g. Fleet enema
Methylnaltrexone (streamlined authority) if opioid-induced
Manual evacuation (ensure PRN analgesia / sedation available)
Consider - is bowel obstruction present?
If pseudo-obstruction, consider neostigmine 0.5mg subcut twice daily (see Appendix - Neostigmine)

Methylnaltrexone
Peripherally acting opioid antagonist
Used for opioid-induced constipation refractory to appropriately titrated  laxatives and enemas

Dose:

12mg subcut (if > 62 kg)
OR 8mg subcut (if 38-61kg)
OR 0.15mg/kg (if <38kg)
Repeat on day 2 if required
If required, can continue to give every second day

Can result in a massive bowel action within an hour. Is a commode required?

Can cause severe abdominal cramps. Ensure subcut hyoscine butylbromide (Buscopan) + subcut opioids available
Contraindicated in bowel obstruction
Dose reduction required in renal failure

In constipation associated with spinal cord compression ->

Oral laxatives
PLUS
Bisacodyl suppository each morning (or every second morning)

Appendix - Phenobarbitone

Phenobarbitone in palliative patients should only be used under the direction of a palliative care specialist. Speak to one before initiating phenobarbitone.

Indications:

Terminal agitation refractory to other treatments (e.g. midazolam > 60mg/day and either haloperidol > 10mg/day or levomepromazine > 100mg/day) (non-PBS indication)
Status epilepticus or recurrent seizures in an imminently dying patient that has been refractory to benzodiazepine therapy

For Refractory Terminal Restlessness or Refractory Terminal Seizures:

Initial dose:

Give phenobarbitone 200mg IM or subcut

If agitation continues, give up to 2 further doses IM or subcut, 30 minutes apart

Starting a continuous subcutaneous infusion:

Commence an infusion at a dose of between 800mg and 1,200mg over 24 hours via CSCI (diluent is water). Use the higher dose for large patients or those who required a larger loading dose. Use the lower dose for other patients.

Additional medications:

Prescribe phenobarbitone 200mg IM or subcut 2-hourly PRN for ongoing agitation

Continue antipsychotics and midazolam initially – these can be discontinued once agitation is well controlled.

Do not stop opioids (phenobarbitone is not an analgesic).

Phenobarbitone Precautions

Stat doses of phenobarbitone subcut have been reported to cause tissue necrosis, therefore IM is preferred

Phenobarbitone is incompatible with other drugs therefore use a separate syringe pump

Dilute to the maximum volume possible to reduce site irritation. Manufacturer recommends diluting 10 times.

Phenobarbitone cannot be mixed with any other medications subcutaneously.